Robert Hoelzle, PhD

Data Scientist

Data scientist and bioinformatician with 11 years' experience in high paced R&D environment, 6 years' experience in bioinformatics programming, and a life-long passion for problem solving. Proficient in Python, R, and Bash with many multivariate modelling and statistics techniques.

Experience

Bioinformatics Research Fellow

2016 – Present The University of Queensland Brisbane, Qld, AUS

- Published 4 peer-reviewed publications (+3 in review), including design of data analysis pipelines in <u>Bash</u>, <u>R</u>, and <u>Python</u> which integrate complex genomic, transcriptomic, and environmental datasets
- Slashed research group's processing time for genomic data by 60% through design of custom <u>Python</u> bioinformatic programs for DNA sequences
- Initiated and maintained consultancies with biotech industry stakeholders for microbiology solutions to soil carbon sequestration, copper bioleaching, and wastewater treatment projects
- Supervised eight research students, and mentored four research professionals, providing guidance for coding and data analysis in <u>Bash</u>, <u>R</u>, and <u>Python</u>

Bioprocess Engineering PhD Student

2012 – 2017 The University of Queensland Brisbane, Qld, AUS

- Published 3 peer-reviewed articles and 1 thesis, including design of data analysis pipelines in <u>Bash</u> and <u>R</u> which integrate complex genomic, proteomic, and environmental datasets
- Discovered and published novel bioplastic production method using custom bioreactors with self-designed environmental control systems in C++

Bioprocess Engineer

2010 – 2012 Green Biologics Ltd Columbus, Ohio, USA

- Programmed environmental control systems in <u>C++</u> for pilot and demonstration scale biofuel reactors, resulting in a commercially operating biofuel plant
- Coordinated governmental lab certification by US National Renewable Energy Laboratory for pilot reactor research facility
- Supervised two research assistants for pilot and demonstration scale reactor development

Skills

Languages

<u>Python</u> (SKLearn, SciPy, Pandas, NumPy, Dash, IBM_DB, FuzzyWuzzy)

<u>R</u> (Vegan, NbClust, RCy3, RStatix, mvabund, Ismeans, spaa, dplyr, tidyr, SpiecEasi)

Bash, T-SQL, SQLite, and C++

Modelling and Statistics

Predictive modelling, generalized linear models, single/multiple linear and polynomial regression, advanced multivariate statistics, multivariate ordination, feature clustering, network analysis

Cloud Infrastructure

IBM Watson Studio, IBM DB2, Galaxy Australia, GitHub

General

Creative problem solving, technical writing and communication, consulting, project management, budget management, team coordination

Education and Certificates

- PhD (2017) The University of Queensland Chemical Engineering
- BSc w/ Honors (2010) The Ohio State University Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering
- Professional Cert (2022) IBM
 Data Science

Community Engagement

- Joint Academic Microbiology Seminars (2018 Pr)
- March for Science Brisbane (2017)
- Engineers without Borders UQ (2015 2016)

Interests

Rock Climbing Home Brewing
Ultimate Frisbee Escape Rooms
Photography Gardening